The next section involves the testicle,
and the first disorder is called cryptorchidism.
This is failure of the testicle
to descend into the scrotal sac.
Let's remind ourselves embryologically
that the testicle normally develops in the abdomen,
and then it descends into the scrotal sac
as the fetus grows.
If it fails to descend, that's called cryptorchidism.
This is the most common congenital male
reproductive abnormality.
It's seen in about 1% of male infants.
Now what I should remind you of is that
most cases would actually resolve
spontaneously.
However, if it doesn't resolve by the age of 2,
then the surgeon would go in and actually
perform a procedure called orcapexy,
where they tack the testicle down into the scrotal sac,
and that's because after the age of 2,
you can begin to get damage to the germ cells,
and that plays into the complication,
which is that there's an increased risk
for testicular atrophy with infertility,
and that's because the testicle normally
needs to be at a lower temperature,
and if it's up high in the body,
it won't be at that low temperature.
The purpose of keeping the testicle
and the scrotal sac is to keep the temperature low,
which is a little lower than the body temperature.
So there'd be an increased risk for testicular atrophy
with infertility if you let it go beyond the age of 2,
and also there's an increased risk for development
of a germ cell tumor called seminoma,
and so basically if these patients don't resolve
by the age of 2, they're going to get orcapexy.
Orchitis refers to inflammation of the testicle.
It can classically be seen with chlamydia,
so chlamydia trachomatis, in particular serotypes D through K,
can lead to orchitis, it's again sexually transmitted disease.
Neisseria gonorrhea can also do it.
E. coli and pseudomonas would be seen in older adults.
Basically, these are the urinary tract infection bugs
that would normally be seen in older adults,
and so they can also spread into the reproductive tract.
And so basically when you think about orchitis,
you think about chlamydia trachomatis, D through K,
and Neisseria in younger sexually active adults,
and then E. coli and pseudomonas in older adults.
Mumps virus can also do it.
Remember that when we talked about mumps,
we mentioned that mumps classically inflames the parotid glands.
However, it can also inflame three other tissues.
You can get infection within the meninges,
giving you an aseptic meningitis.
You can get pancreatitis,
and then finally you can get orchitis.
And so if there's orchitis,
there would be a increased risk for infertility.
But remember that orchitis is not usually seen
until the patients are greater than the age of 10.
And finally, you can get something called autoimmune orchitis,
in which there's autoimmune destruction of the testicular tissue.
And the classic hallmark of this
is that you get granulomas that involve the tubules of the testicle.
So granulomatous inflammation of the testicle,
you think about two things.
You think about TB,
and you think about autoimmune orchitis.
And of course, you can prove TB by doing an AFB stain
and trying to find the acid fast bacilli
that would be indicative of TB.
And also in TB,
you often would see necrotizing granulomas,
whereas in autoimmune orchitis,
the granulomas would be non-necrotizing.
Testicular torsion occurs
when you have twisting of the spermatic cord,
which then leads to hemorrhagic infarction of the testicle.
It's a very simple principle.
You've got the spermatic cord,
and there's obviously blood artery and vein going in and out.
And then you've got the testicle hanging on that cord.
If you twist the testicle around that cord,
you are going to close off the thin-walled vein,
but the thick-walled artery will remain open.
And so blood will come in, but blood can't go out.
And if blood comes in but can't go out,
that's going to eventually lead to infarction.
And so in this particular case,
they get a hemorrhagic infarction
because blood keeps going in,
but you're not going to get flow across the organ
because you blocked the venous drainage.
So that lack of blood flow across the organ
will then result in infarction.
And of course, it would be hemorrhagic
because blood is still coming in
and because this is a loosely organized tissue.
Remember that to get hemorrhagic infarction,
you need two things.
You need blood going into the space
after the tissue has died,
plus you need a loosely organized tissue.
So that's what I say here about testicular infarction.
It occurs with twisting of the spermatic cord,
which leads to hemorrhagic infarction.
It can be due to congenital failure of the testes
to attach to the inner lining of the scrotum.
Now remember that the testes at their base
are normally attached to the inner lining of the scrotum.
And so if they're not attached,
then you can easily get a twisting
of the testicle on that cord.
The classically presents an adolescence
and it presents with sudden testicular pain
and an absent cremasteric reflux.
The cremasteric reflux is
when you take a tongue depressor
and scrape it along the inner aspect of the thigh.
That would cause the scrotum,
the muscles of the scrotum to actually contract
and it would draw the scrotum upward.
And so in this particular case,
because the nerves that are necessary
for that cremasteric reflux
are also coming through the cord,
in this particular case,
when the tissue is dead
and you tried to scrape with a tongue depressor
along the inner thigh,
you wouldn't get that cremasteric reflux.
And that's an important clinical finding.
And again, it's high yield for exams as well.
Here's a picture of a testicular torsion
with a hemorrhagic infarction of the testicle.
You can see that the testicle
has basically been reduced to a sack of blood.
A varicocele is when you have dilation
of the spermatic vein due to impaired drainage.
And that's gonna present a scrotal swelling
with a bag of worms appearance.
Now, the idea here is that
all of the veins become dilated
and you see them on the surface of the scrotum.
That's the key thing.
And so it looks like a bag of worms
and you can feel it
and it also feels like a bag of worms.
Varicoceles are usually left-sided
and they're associated
with left-sided renal cell carcinoma as well.
This is particularly high yield
because it goes back to anatomy.
So I just wanna take a moment
to draw what's going on on the left side.
Let's go back to the whiteboard.
Here's the inferior vena cava
and you've got the renal vein coming in
to the inferior vena cava.
So this is again the inferior vena cava.
Now the idea here is that
when you look at the spermatic vein
on the left side,
the spermatic vein goes into the renal vein
and then eventually the renal vein
then drains into the inferior vena cava.
And so this creates an extra step
for that drainage
and therefore because there's an extra step,
there's an increased risk
for developing varicoceles on the left side.
Whereas on the opposite side,
if this were the right side, for example,
this is the renal vein,
the spermatic vein goes directly
into the inferior vena cava
so it doesn't have to go through that extra space.
And so it's less likely to develop varicoceles
on that right side.
Now at the same time,
let's say that a patient has a renal cell carcinoma.
You're well aware of the fact
that renal cell carcinoma loves to invade the renal vein.
It's one of the carcinomas
that likes to go into the vein.
And so when renal cell carcinoma
goes into the renal vein,
we're gonna get blocking of the renal vein
which would block the drainage of the spermatic vein
and therefore give you a varicocele
in particular on the left side.
So this is super high yield.
It shows up on exams all the time.
The varicoceles are usually left-sided
and they're associated
with left-sided renal cell carcinoma.
Also, varicoceles can be seen
in a large percentage of infertile males.
And the idea here,
one of the theories here
is that if you've got a varicocele,
you've got a lot of warm blood piling up
in the scrotal sac.
And if you've got a lot of warm blood piling up,
that potentially is going to warm
the temperature of the overall testicle
which would then result in infertility.
That hasn't been proven,
but anyway, it's one theory
of why there's this association.
A hydrocele is when you have fluid collection
within the tunica vaginalis.
Let's pretend this is the testicle.
Remember that there is a layer of cirrhosa
that's on the testicle
and it sort of comes around
and also attaches to the scrotal skin out here.
And so this is called the tunica vaginalis.
Now, it normally has a minimal amount of fluid
and it's really imperceptible.
However, when you fill this with fluid,
as you fill it with fluid,
that's going to result in fluid building
in the scrotal sac,
and that's called a hydrosele.
Now, it's associated with incomplete closure
of the process vaginalis in infants.
Now, remember that when you form the scrotum,
it actually is an invagination of the peritoneum
that comes down like this
to form the tunica vaginalis.
So if this is not sealed properly up here,
then you can have a connection with the peritoneum
which then could provide fluid to this region
and that's what you would see in infants.
A failure, and this again is a failure
of the closure of the process vaginalis.
At the same time, it's possible to see it in adults
and if you see it in adults,
it's due to blockage of lymphatic drainage classically.
Now, this presents a scrotal swelling
and it can be transluminated
which means that if you took light
and you shined it across the scrotum,
you would be able to get light through there
and that's because you don't have a solid mass,
you just have a bag of fluid.
This is what the hydroseal looks like.
You just have a swollen scrotum
and that's because it's loaded with fluid.
And that concludes this section.
Thank you.